of the use of artificial intelligence in our
societies so today let's go back to today's
discussion and workshop i'm very much looking
forward to it of course and i would like now maybe
to to give the floor to geriv yatri to say a few
words on the side of early kid before moving to
the representative of japanese embassy sheriff the
floor thank you sebastian i hope you can hear me
um good morning good afternoon konichiwa to all of
you so i am uh vietnamese i'm located in in japan
and i'm uh in charge of the r d activity for the
leaky group uh for the agr region um through that
as uh sebastian said it could be uh it looks a
bit strange to see a leaky has been part of this
event in fact first of all what is the alley
kid for the one which don't know early kid
for our colleagues in japan maybe helikit
is a company supplying industrial gases
in fact we have been in japan for more than 100
years so we are not a newcomer in japan and of
course um being part of this exchange program is
with french and japan is we say obvious for us
for that's one reason the second reason is that
somehow innovation has been at the heart of the
company and the company has been created a
long time ago with by an inventor which has
been exploring many fields and i'm sure at some
point of his career has been touching the art also
and now what's uh is very much the focus of
the group is of course the energy transition
with the development of the hydrogen society
but also looking at any technology that will
allow us to develop a sustainable future and this
question of ai is certainly one of the topics
that is uh very important in our mind
so the topics of the day is definitively
not directly linked between a link between ai
and the we say unusual operation that we have in
the company but somehow we have the feeling that
such technology or such new technology i would say
which is really disruptive addressing uh certainly
the way we uh we feel we touch we get in contact
uh with uh things um cannot be only looked at from
an industrial point of view from a technical from
an engineer i'm i'm i'm very bad artist i'm an
engineer you know dealing with numbers dealing
with mechanics dealing with these kind of things
um but i'm still convinced that uh when we touch
technology and new technology and especially in
the digital world we have to look at it from a
different angle and this is one of the reasons
why we have been funding this uh this year and
this program at the front france japan since the
beginning of the of the creation was to be able to
approach topics from more human science point of
view and uh honestly um that's uh i think it's a
very interesting it's complimentary to what we
do and therefore i'm very delighted to be part
of you today to listen i will be mostly listening
uh but uh again i have the opportunity to meet uh
itosan in paris a few months ago when i visit
paris and i was really interesting and i think we
had a very nice discussion in our research center
in paris and i think i'm looking forward for the
presentation of today thank you very much for the
invitation thank you thank you very much genre
for your kind words so now i would like
to before the what you uh are waiting
for and you expected before the talk by
uh i would like to to give the floor to
mr taken uti from japanese embassy in paris to say
a few words in the name of of japanese authorities
thank you for the kind introduction my
name is yosuke take enoji in charge of
science and technology policy at the embassy of
japan in france and first of all on behalf of
the embassy i would like to congratulate you on
the successful organization of today's workshop
as kobe continues to impose uh
restrictions around the world
science and technology related events like
this are still not as active as before
and under such circumstances i'm very delighted
that today's event has come to be held and i
guess it was not an easy task to prepare so i i
would express my sincere gratitude especially to
dr coitro etto and fundacion france japan and airy
kids and old members involved for their efforts
and looking at the science and technology policies
of both countries in france research planning law
has been enacted that sets out the 10-year
research strategy starting in 2021 and similarly
japan has just formulated the science technology
and innovation basic plan which will run for
five years starting in 2021 as well and the main
pillars for both plants are social transformation
and strengthening of research capabilities
and education and human resource development
and i see there are so many similarities in the
challenges that japan and france are facing and
needless to say among the social transformation
brought about by advanced technologies the impact
of ai is enormous and this is evident from reading
the ai strategies established in both countries
and discussing how we can make rapid social
transformation more acceptable to society is
as important important models as technological
development itself so i understand that the
uh the theme of today's workshop is to pursue
the role of art as a solution to this question
which is a very interesting point of view and i
look forward to the presentations and discussions
or the participants today and finally i would
like to conclude my greetings with the wish
that today's workshop will be an opportunity
for new collaborations across research fields
and the borders thank you very much thank you
very much for for your kind words mr takenuchi
and i think now it's time to to give the
floor to our colleague and friend ethos so
we we hope you you will enjoy this
workshop and enjoy the discussion as well
so the floor is yours etosa oh
thank you very much my name is
the first i'd like to say thank you for all
participants especially for speakers and audience
so i'd like to start my
presentation without for a moment
okay i'd like to start my presentation
my title of the presentation is art
brings the future to our society
and i am a 2021 ffj educate hero at foundation
class japan and also i am a researcher at ice
first of all i would like to thank everyone
who helped me make this workshop push first
i would like to thank mr john erws from airlift
corporation and professor as a service channel cba
foundation from japan who made this
fellowship position thank you very much
and i would like to also thank my colleague
at ffj and fabian son and ito san jose
and my colleague in japan and thank you for all
before getting into the main topic let me
explain the differences from the algebra
the initial plan was to investigate the
cognitive differences in ai between japan
and the west and however it turned out to
be difficult due to the reason shown here
therefore i have switched the plan and i have
defined the final object to investigate the
relationship between ai and advanced technology
in europe i appreciate your understanding
and first let me introduce myself i
have been working as an artist since 90s
then in 2002 i joined ice and started working as
a researcher i would like to introduce to my works
they have in common is that their works
and that makes the internet visible
this work is very proper you can see a world map
on the screen on this map you can see the user's
web hopping trajectory for example let's say
you are looking at the website in the u.s
then you click a link to europe then virtually
you have jumped from the u.s to europe
by analyzing internet traffic in real time and i
could visualize the trajectory of web browsing we
published this work in 1996 and we won the grand
prix of three architectural income at that time
the work became our permanent
exhibit at the arctic asset
we want the grand prix of preservator the press
prize is the most prestigious award in this field
this exhibit is a hands-on model of the
internet this work shows how internet works
you can see a white table in front of you and this
is a timer here you can make a packet with broken
whiteboards the first edibles are for an
address and the last edibles are full data
you can only send one character
at a time then press send button
the pocket goes through the internet
from the long car moves the pocket
from the local area network to another
network so this is a built-in table
and then a packet go from the
out to the environment then
and this is the destination parameter
the pocket go to the display of the timer
then the packet goes into the display
and you can see the full head of
the packet which is the character a
and we created this work in
2001 and you can still see
it in the region right now if you have a
chance to uh visit tokyo please stop by
what i would like to explain here is
a period in the 90s this age was a
very early stage of the internet at that
time the internet was adverse technology
this works explains how the internet
works for the general public
since 2002 i have been a researcher at ice
continuing my research demand how we
can design a place for co-creation
the key concept of my research is that the
users should design the system this picture
is over famous architects christopher alexander
he said that users should design the architecture
if we do that we won't need an
object anymore instead he created
a pattern language to make this concept portion a
method to design architectural result architects
this idea is a key concept of my research
we created several co-creation platforms that
connect various fields based on this concept
the most significant achievement
was the niconico archive data
we created a platform that connects the general
public with professional researchers even if
they are not working as a professional researchers
there are still people doing research we call them
wild researchers and we have created a
place for them to present their research
with us we started this project in 2011
and held nine large skeleton projects
the first simple gym attracted a 110 000
audience on the internet the total number of
viewers was over 650 000 people since then
i have expanded my activities as follows
and i would like to share the latest research
results of our research in january of this year
we published this paper crash word 74 facial
emojis on the balance and arousal processes
presentness and intensity we published this paper
in scientific reports and it is
pressure released from nature asia
now i would like to start explaining and
explaining this fellowship with the result
and first i asset the research question asks
what is the role of art in advanced technology
then i would like to move on to
the background method and findings
first there are already some pioneering studies on
the relationship between ai and art first of all
there is a book area for creation by prohibition
now from university he is also speaker of this
workshop his book is a very detailed description
of how can we use ai to develop human creativity
also professor sofia audrey's book art in the
age of machine learning is published last year
go back to the history of computer art this
research is also excellent also the mdpi journal
arts has a special issue on the
machine as artists in 1999 and 2019
which includes 17 people and 17 papers
all of which are very worthwhile
and let's start with the
explanation of observations
in europe i visited various events and
centers where art and science are related
earth earth electronic is the most significant
example in europe this center began as a media
art festival in 1979 the oldest and the biggest
in the world and they started pre-architecture in
1987 the award is the most highly
regarded in the media out here in 1996
they opened the architectural center as
shown in this picture and they also started
an rnd center called a future level in the same
building and my relationship with architecture is
strong i received the pre-architect three
times including the grand prix of 1997.
from my point of view and the most significant
result of future lab is spark cells they started
the project in 2012 to draw textures in the sky
using drones they named this project spark cells
the meaning is pixels in space i saw the
initial launch event at mainz in 2012
in honest i felt that the light was so weak and
unreliable at that time but this project grew
steadily in 2015 they started doing research
with intel and they developed this project
far away in 2021 intel drew a symbol mark of
tokyo 2020 at the opening ceremony of tokyo
and they held the reception festival in 2021 again
but it was a hybrid event usually the festival
attracts so many artists from all over the world
but this year there was almost no artist from
overseas it was a private event but i had i found
an excellent exhibit a feature level also produces
exhibits from the fosa ascertain center in this
video you can see eleven monitors in front of you
in these monitors you can see the hidden layers of
dna as you know there are many layers behind the
neural network and this exhibit shows
the mechanisms of dna very well in detail
and they use the cnn a convolutional neural
network with the ouija 16 network i think this
is a simple idea but effective by showing the
layers all at once we can see how the dna works
uh after i had a chance to interview mr hideyaki
ugawa the co-director of futura i was very
impressed by his words just as the water comes out
when you twist the stuff the future comes out when
you twist the top of the earthening center he
is also an artist still creating their artworks
uh events like this artistic festival are
now taking place in other cities in paris
there is a similar there is a similar event
called the nemo vienna they held the event at
sun cattle at various other locations in paris and
they designed this event to connect science and
art i participated in this event and i felt that
the direction was so close to the arizona festival
and there are events called makeup here where
are people who like to make things gather
and show their creation make up here events are
all over the world on the non-makeup campus was
outstanding quality and also i am a i am
a director of discover a mini makeup here
then i met several artists and interviewed them
first let me introduce la machine the moving
giant elephant of nat in the city of land the
big elephant carried a lot of people around the
city every day i had the chance to interview the
artistic director mr francois bravo and according
to him it is important to have such huge artwork
moving around the public open city and open space
i felt that this is rubbed
by the citizens very much
from class radiology and dora rogers was i was
particularly interested in his focus on movement
and according to him movement is a
language a machine at the mechanical organs
the next artist is a scott adam the picture on the
left is a finished painting the video on the right
side shows how she is drawing as you can see it is
just a simple sketch without an outline but the ai
automatically draws the content with human body
uh scotland has a background in art and he also
graduated from the mit media level so he is very
good at computer science and he studied drawing
and sculpture in hilo lands in italy i think his
paintings under the influence of michelangelo
i had the opportunity to interview him and
it was fascinating i think he was a
great philosophy as an artist who uses ai
in particular i would like to emphasize the
word for an artist hero is sometimes due to
i think this is a natural appeal of media art
creating art through a repeated experimentation
uh next up is a perennial motherhood as
you can see he created a computer graphics
image that looks like japanese superheroes
he didn't make these images by hand
but he designed an algorithm to create superheroes
based on that algorithm the program generated
countless superheroes shaped automatically
this kind of art is what we call generative art
i interviewed him also he was born in san
paulo grazer and watched japanese tv programs
in childhood so it was there that he
came into contact with japanese culture
and began to create this kind of work
so i would like to explain uh what i
have learned from the jesus experience
uh first of all i would like to say that
i have been moved to more places and
one that the most impressed me was a good shovel
this growth survey is a cave mirror that exists
about 36 000 years old lascaux cave is uh two
twelve uh twenty thousand years old so this
is probably the oldest jab mirror we see here
a replica of grotesque called grothshove too
although it is a replica it is so realistic it
looks like real thing is here here is a mirror
of lions but it exists with the same reality
i was very impressed by this and before i came
to france i thought that this europa was a
place where a modern western culture has
developed but that was not the case i mean the
cost of mediterranean sea is where civilization
began i was finally able to understand this
then what the forces that drive the progress of
civilization the science fiction novelist neil
stephenson invented the term metabolism in his
novel a snowflash in this in this book he says
that there are some layers of language and the
civilization progresses through the power of
crossing between these layers in his words a code
or a problem language is the latest language layer
a language defines our thinking it is very
difficult to share a concept that has not been
yet been put into us please imagine
this how would you tell yourself
2019 about the changes brought by
copic 19 i think you feel you will find
it a bit difficult once the common language is
established and sharing concepts become special
another load of human in society is
dictated by a major technological changes
the industrial revolution was governed by natural
laws in particular how to control the engine was
very important locomotive automobiles blooms
and later places are all powered by engines
please remember that the term
engineering come from comes from energy
on the other hand the ideal deportation
is governed by language so when we can
express it in a language we can execute it for
example we often compare the hacker to a wizard
when a wizard just a spell it became true in
this situation just means a programming language
next and let's consider the ai devotion
that is taking place i believe that
air is governed by imagination in ai
everything exists in a probabilistic way
there is no rigid distinction between 0 or 1.
from my point of view this is closer to paintings
than to language i mean in other words what can be
visualized can be executed i remind scott eaton's
statement that artists control ai with their
imagination and idea is a perfect example of this
so i would like to return to the research question
what is the role of art in advanced technology
my findings are to be a source of imagination
and expand the possibility to advanced
technology so i would like to end
my presentation thank you very much
then
can i go progress yes please i give you the floor
to organize the round table think thank you very
much and there will be i think there will be
many questions and congratulations of course so
on your talk but i think in order to
uh to have a good discussion it's good
to move to the round table and then
to have to have the the discussion
okay thank you very much and then uh let's
start to uh session one so in session one
we have uh presentation for autos first and
we will have a presentation from now tokui
from university toku sensei and could
you please start your presentation
hi yes thank you yeah thank you very much do you
hear me uh yes thank you okay so um hi everyone
uh thank you for having me so let me start
my presentation so can i share my screen
yes normally you can share
you have the right to share
yes okay sorry so today i want to talk about ai
and creativity and before that let me introduce
myself so my name is naotoki i'm an artist and
researcher and also i'm a founder and ceo of
tokyo-based art collective cosmo and also
i also organized a computational creativity
laboratory at ko university in japan so today
i want to talk about uh ai and creativity and
especially the main scene of my talk is this so is
ai capable of creating something new and original
maybe more precisely is ai capable
of helping us create something new
and original rather than imitating
what we humans have already created
so why i got interested in this topic is this like
i i entered a university of university of tokyo in
1995 and joined um laboratory i mean ai laboratory
there in 1998 and also at the same time i started
djing by myself and i got kind of obsessed
with music and i started thinking like i
want to create music i want to create
new music nobody ever listened to so
but uh i don't play any musical instruments
and i don't barely read musical scores
so how can i make interesting music so
naturally i turn to programming and ai
so here i'm not interested in optimizing and
streamlining the music making process to make
more hip songs more economically a lot
of love instead uh i'm interested in
diversification and deviation so how
can i make uh something unique music
uh
you know basically new music and
here i have a agenda of my talk today
so i want to talk about three topics
um person is misusable ai tools okay so the
importance of music tools you can misuse
and you may find it a little bit strange to
use the world misuse in the discussion of ai
but when you look back when you look back
the history of music and other creative field
you may realize that it is in fact the history of
misused and misappropriated new technologies so
one of uh recalling patterns is when an artist
used new technology in a way the original inventor
didn't intend or imagine it is when new form of
expression emerged so the prime example of these
misused technology is for example time tables
and samplers so for as for turntable you are
not supposed to touch and move vinyl records right
and samplers are also in bed invented to imitate
expensive physical instruments such as pianos
and violins but the inventor didn't expect
users to appropriate and sample somebody else's
records music such as you know funky drummers
or aiming brakes or whatever and uh when we think
about the current status of ai music tools or ai
creative tools in general you see like
both extreme ends of the spectrum here
at um on one hand you have like uh programmer
oriented tools like uh so you need to install
python and and tensorflow and you need
cuda of course and uh you know you have to
get used to these tools to make something unique
or something new and i'm sure this some artists
can learn and train themselves to you know get
used to these tools but usually it's not the case
and at the other end of spectrum we have very
well packaged uh tools ai tools so with one click
you can generate music or with one click the ai
can edit your uh photo images you know and uh
that's in some case that's good but if i think
if the tool is too well packaged then you cannot
misuse or you cannot use these tools in
your own way or in your own creative way so
i think we need something in bit in between
these two end of uh two ends of spectrum and i
call it misusable ai tools and following this
principle i created a simple ai tool for musicians
and it is an ableton live uh famous uh digital
audio workshop uh sorry workstation software uh
and uh yeah so this is um ableton live struggling
and what it does is it allows you as artists to
train your own ai model within this software
so you don't have to deal with python and cuda
so only thing you need to do is just collect music
data in this case midi files and drag and drop
on the device and voila you got a trained
model on this device and you can generate
new listens continuously and you can
i hope you can hear the audio
and good thing about this tool is you
can actually misuse this tool so you can
train your own model with very
obscure data set or i don't know
this this device is meant for listener
generation but you can train your own model with
melody data for example and see what comes out
okay that's one small project i did in 2020 and
i want to talk about uh the second topic here
uh which is embracing the uncertainty or
errors ai brings so this is a visualization of
the output of the same model i just introduced and
this is useful and great and also you can use this
tool to generate something unique but still
you need your own training data to train this
product and maybe you can say like it this
model is still imitating human creation
so 2017 i created something called neural
beatbox so what i did is to combine this
generation model the same rhythmization
model with a sound classification model
and you can play this new beatbox on this website
newellbitbox.net so if you are interested please
take a look and what i did was to integrate
the sound classification model with the
resume generation model and genetic generated
listening patterns will be played with the
instant drum kit the sound classification
model created out of recorded sound materials
so we created this website
during the covet lockdown so
on this website you can create uh your own
beats with the help board ai and you can share
your system with your friends so that you
can enjoy your instant beatbox session
and i should mention that the soundcraft
classification is not perfect of course but
that's what we wanted we wanted to
deviate from what humans you know but
okay so what i just said is like this so when
you try to create something new and unique
you want to deviate and branch out from the
conventions or common senses and we hope
it will be a manifestation of creativity
but sometimes it especially from the
conventional perspective this deviation
can be just a mistake or an error right
so we need to know how to embrace the mistakes
and how to you know you have to know
how to uh differentiate mistakes from you know
manifestation of creativity and uh so this
uh era and creativity is one of my main theme
i think so the other project where i embrace
the uncertainty of ai is this ai dj project uh
it's a back-to-back dj session with me and ai dj
and so aid just selects and plays
sometimes unexpected songs but this uncertainty
leads to very interesting dj performance
yeah so sometimes ai
selects something i didn't
expect or i couldn't imagine and but the this
is unexpectedness was so interesting as a dj
and we are so fortunate to
have opportunities to play
various locations including google i o in
san francisco and scopiton festival in nont
and so we extended this scene and we
turned it into a real-time ai jump session
i i hope you can listen to
you can share the audio now
anyway uh so
instead of letting ait select existing music
we made an air system that makes music on
stage in real time so in this performance
three ai models namely resume generation model
uh baseline generation and loop selection
uh interact with each each other and keep
improvising a dance track so i as a dj
intervene the process of by manipulating mixer
and adding sound with a turntable so it's
not a disc jockey anymore it's more
like a machine jerky or an aisle key
okay so finally i want to talk about
uh this like pushing ai to the edge
and so let's get back to your original question is
ai capable of creating something new and original
so here i want to talk about generative adversary
network so it's a famous framework so i'm not
going to explain it in detail so but it's
so famous for the capability of generating
very realistic faces but here i want to
use it for again listen patterns and uh
in this in this model i added the conditioning
input so you can specify the
junk and and generate patterns
do you hear the audio i cannot hear
i cannot hear it somehow good no no
sorry dick again
okay
okay so
again i added a conditional input so that you
can specify the journal of generated design
patterns but it's not very interesting so i
added another discriminator to this uh model
the discommit sorry i added another
discriminator that is for classifying
uh the journals of generated muse generative
reasons so the generator generator is
trained to confuse the additional discriminator
as well so that it can generate realistic reason
pattern that don't belong to any existing genres
in the training data set so this is the result
i hope you can hear i don't i cannot hear
let's just go
okay so what here i wanted to realize uh
realize uh like a target war between the
conventions and deviation so now ai is telling
is trying to tell which deviation is good and
interesting and this is i believe what
human artists do actually and finally i
want to introduce one of my favorite quotes of
scott adams he's a comic famous comic writer of uh
dewbert comics ship and it goes like this uh
creativity is allowing yourself to make mistake
art is knowing which ones to keep and in in the
context of ai and creativity i think ai is a tool
that makes that helps you make interesting
meaningful amusing mistakes and consequently
it helps you to create something new and original
okay finally uh as etosan introduced i published
this book in last year and i'm working on english
translation and hopefully i can deliver it
within a few months okay so thank you so much
uh thank you very much to question say i love
their presentation very much and i'm sorry about
audio trouble no no no problem i have so
many questions for professor tokui but for
on this program i will do the presentation
for session one uh all then we will have a
ten minutes regret q1a so i'd like to do this
and next this next present so next presenter
can you hear me yes yes okay thank you very much
for accepting uh the speaker of this lecture
would you please start your
presentation as i can say okay
here you are
can you see it yes perfect all right so
uh my presentation will be by about my erc
european research council advanced grant
reach raising co-creativity in cyber human
musicianship first of all let me present ircam
the place where i'm i am a researcher so irkam
is instituted the coordination acoustic music with
actually a part of saint george pompidou in paris
it was created by famous conductor and composer
pierre bules in the uh 70s when the when the
sun pompidou was created and it is the the music
music and sound research parts of centro pompidou
so we have a three part in irkam a research lab
called science and technology of sound and music
who is operated by cnrs and strawberry
university and irkam of course and the
minister of the culture communication we
have we have a music creation department
with concert halls and composers in residence and
music commissions etc and we have an education
department where we have a master's program
first for young scientists and another program
in technology for musicians so it's a very
original model of innovation and creativity
uh where we have artists that are
immersed into a research context
all right so in irkam i have created a team called
music representation team years ago and now it has
become the biggest team in irkam and we have
a lot of researchers on ai and creativity for
artistic purposes specifically music
so we have five poles in this team so
certain of these polls are concerned with music
composition formalization uh formal approaches
to music but we have the three poles here are
really concerned with artificial intelligence
so reach is really the the the project that i will
be uh speaking about acid is a a project that is
highly oriented towards the machine learning for
creative applications and activities is really
oriented towards the idea of time and how you
write and control the time in an interactive setup
so to give an example uh there is a here
is a program that i wrote many years ago
and has now become the standard all over the world
for a computer-assisted composition it's called
open music and we have published three books where
thousands of composers explain how they would use
open music to create new music so open music
is actually a programming language but it is a
visual programming language so composers learn how
to program more easily because it's totally visual
and they can design new musical application so
this is not the artificial intelligence approach
this is the formal approaches where composers
actually have to specify the algorithm that they
want to use in order to create music after having
created open music with of course with my team
i have moved to the idea of creating
intelligent interaction with agents
with creative agents so we are moving closer
to artificial intelligence and again quite a
number of years ago i created with colleagues
the omax paradigm of intelligent interaction so
you see omax is really the simple idea that you
have intelligent agent feed with ai that are able
to listen to music either in offline or in real
time that are able simultaneously to learn so
apply a machine learning model create a model so
a mirror of musical memory simultaneously scan and
navigate the memory in order to generate new
materials and propose this new materials to
the musician and then you have reaction
reactions on both sides the musician will
react to the ai the ai will react to the musician
and we have this creative loop so omax had a lot
of hairs and descendants and you see many
popular systems that have been derived from
or original researchers uh on the omax paradigm
and notably all the work that is done right now at
sony music and now at spotify
is uh that was that was um um
work done was by francois pache was immediately
derived from our original research work at uh
on omax so homage has become a very important
paradigm and we have moved from this paradigm to
something even more uh interesting right now but
let me let me just give an idea of what this uh
interaction paradigm is about so before learning
the system must listen so you must have a
perception perception aware system of listening
we call this machine or artificial listening so
that we're gonna we're gonna uh segment uh the
the the stream of music into uh musical in it
that that will be distribute distributed over
some mathematical structure maybe a geometry
and we will discover with cognitive algorithm an
alphabet symbolic alphabet structure even though
we we are dealing with audio we will discover a
symbolic alphabet structure of on the musical unit
that will deliver a symbol extreme so from the
symbol extreme we will learn a model so we will
use a number of machine learning algorithm and
then regenerate and render new sequences and the
three processes listen learn and generate are real
time and concurrent and they are both cooperative
concurrent and cooperative so the the nice
drawing that you see here is the visual
representation of a musical sequence that has
been learned in real time by omax and all the
colored arcs that you see are actually actually
actually connecting different places of the music
with regard to similarity so because we have
this co this connection created by the ai
we have a kind of cartography of a map of the
music and the system just have to navigate around
this map to create new sequences that will be
statistically coherent with the material that
was learned but still creative and novel so
you see here in this model you have the the
musician who is for instance improvising and there
is a double loop he's listening to other musicians
and but he's also he or she listening to
uh to uh themselves and also listening to
its sound memories so himself or herself in the
past and the memory is a virtual part because
it is constituted by all that the musician
has played all that the other musicians are
playing and all that the mission has
ever played or learned in his life so
this is all virtual and this is exactly the
musical memory that the ai system is simulating
i'm hearing some music coming from somewhere
okay okay okay so so max is like you know this
zero point here in this graph that represents two
dimensions where you have the reactive dimension
the system reacts instantly to a to musician and
the planning dimension where the the user can
actually plan behaviors like compose for instance
a harmonic grid or any composition so omax is
really at zero because it is not really planning
and it is not reactive but it has a lot of machine
learning so then we have we have developed more
intelligent systems like the stomach system where
we have a high level of reactivity we have
developed the important system where we have
a high level of planning and now we are working
on a hybrid system where we would have a good
compromise between being totally reactive to what
the live musicians are doing and also having some
planning and being able to develop interesting
and sophisticated and structured musical processes
so here is the the general diagram the that
we are now exploring in the rich uh project
where you have some musical input musical
signal you have a machine listening
unit that creates a symbolic signal stream
you have a learning unit that will do some
machine learning uh statistical probabilistic
probabilistical or deep learning that will learn
a model and that will give back some information
to the uh to the listening machine so it will
help the listening machine to improve itself
so the learning will create a memory model
where we will have an interaction agent that will
query the model in order to create new musical
material but that will still be listening to the
musical stream in the input so the interacting
agent will be able also to be reactive and not
only creative and generative and the user will
be able to specify scenarios so to compose some
music but then the interacting model will be able
to give feedback control to the scenario unit in
order to be able to generate artificial scenarios
that will be interacting with the user general
so this is a highly sophisticated architecture
that will be able to generate very interesting
musical experiments so now let me show you just
two two-minute video where you will see some
example or where we have uh what we have
reached so far you will see you will see a pianist
playing at some point you will hear three singers
edit piaf elizabeth schwarzkopf and b
holidays who are very famous singers
so we have used audio archives but the
ai which will totally uh re-improvise
the audio archives in order to align the
improvisation with what the pianist is doing
and when it comes i'll do my best
oh
from which i'm never wrong
oh sorry
huh
um
okay so you have seen two examples one was
an offline example where the ai has learned
a lot of materials from the three singers and
then is able to recompose and re-improvise
in the audio domain but as well also in
the video domain uh the music and in the
last part of the video you have seen a real time
example where the system captures and learned uh
his model in real time uh from what the musician
is uh actually performing and is able to instantly
uh interact and have a dialogue with the
musician so every time you were listening
to the saxophone sound and the musician was
not obviously not playing his instrument
it was the ai playing and proposing a dialogue to
the to the musician okay recently we have begun
a national research agency project called mercy
makes musical reality with creative instruments
where we have an industrial partner
called high vibe and high vibe has been
has obtained a lot of awards in the industrial
world for instance there is the challenge
award of the the best uh the the best uh
startup for uh 2021 and they are designing
a active acoustic system that uh where
they transform material devices into uh
acoustic
diffusion system and they have created they have
created a new instrument called the high-vibe
guitar that is equipped with actuators and sensors
and computing power inside the guitar and when
where you can you can have some processing of
the sound of the guitar that is rendered not by
a loudspeaker but by the body the wooden body of
the guitar itself so it gives the the musician the
feeling that the instrument is really reacting to
what uh he's doing so here he's here's an example
and another
so so what we want to do is to be able to embed
the artificial intelligence into the instrument so
this instrument is not only capable of extending
the sound of the instrumentist but also to add an
intelligent musical layer to what the musician is
doing and maybe to co-improvise with the musician
and this is what we call co-creativity when
we have a situation an interactive situation
where a musician and a computer system
are able to co-create or co-improvise
and this is where we get to the
rich project that has just begun
the last year where we are kind of uh
wrapping up and summing up all this uh
big experience in uh writing ai system for uh
interactive music creation uh where we want to
really really focus on what i call co-creativity
between human and ai emphasizing that creativity
is an emerging dynamics resulting from
complex interaction between actors so
it cannot be understood by considering each
agent's production in separation but on the
contrary you have to consider the the really
the uh the sum of the behaviors of the agents
so uh this frees us from the concept of artificial
creativity art artificial intelligence in
the art because creativity is not a state that
you are trying to reach it's a dynamical effect
an emergent effect of interaction in a complex
system so you cannot you can never catch really
what creativity or co-creativity is in a
static way it will only emerge in the time
of interaction this is what we the idea that we
defined in reach so cyber human co-creativity
will appear when you have emergence of
cohesive or contrasting joint behaviors
that that you are not able to reduce to individual
processes and then you will have operation of
non-linear regime of event and structure formation
that will create core evolutions of forms and
this happens because you have cross-learning
processes where the machine learns in real time
from the musician but the musician learns in real
time from the machine or international in general
agents that can be artificial or human
learn from one another in a cross
way and this will create complex
feedback loops and reinforcement
mechanism mechanism that will favor the
the emergent the emergent mechanism so
as a cyber physical system like the guitar for
instance is a cyber physical system they create
an interaction continuity between digital and
physical world now we want to propose the term
cyber audience for systems that create a synergy
between the digital models and the human mind the
human creativity so this is the the structure
of reach but mainly what we have is two central
tasks that that are kind of converging one to the
other one is to augment the digital agent's id
abilities with better ai algorithms enhance
creativity autonomy sensitivity to context but
also cyber physical extension like the guitar so
they can act in the material world on the other
side we will take the human and get it closer to
the digital agent by augmenting the human ability
by interfacing them into embedded mixed realities
so for instance the the creative guitar that we
are doing with iv is our first mixed reality
instrument so something that augments the
the natural reality by a digital augmentation so
the rich artistic impact is huge recently we had
the concert at the maison de la jolla music with
the orchest national the the jazz and they were
playing with or algorithm that were interacting in
real time with the whole orchestra which was which
is more than 20 musicians we have we have issued a
a new record and a book called artistic where you
can listen to all this interact the interactive
concert with ai and you have 200 of 200 pages of
critical analysis and commentary of the of the
phenomenon of uh ai in uh in art a lot of concerts
festivals uh etc where all systems are actually
uh used in in in real life and i will just show
a one minute video where you will see the same
kind of human augmentation but here is the video
so we use the archive of binaries concert at
the montreux jazz festival and the archives is
controlled by the ai in order that it's able to
react in real time to what the pianist is doing
then
andy
red
so uh thank you for your
attention and i will stop here
thank you very much and say your
presentation is very interesting and um
i felt to tell this earlier for our
audience if you have any questions
please post questions to the chat
we will have a q a session or q
going to say like could you please start
your presentation okay do you hear me
okay i think you are
seeing my screen right uh i i'm sorry uh
you have to monitor yeah that's a problem
okay
left side
wait a minute i will activate the second screen um
maybe you can screen you can share
not for a monitor for only a window
oh
do you see my screen no no not yet
no you don't see anything
and it's coming and maybe we
can wait for a few seconds
sorry for that i will disconnect my second screen
i don't know what is happening
um
zoom is not really working well for me
of course okay to share a full monitor
is that okay with you do you see my screen now
did you see my screen no no no
i don't know what is going on
um i propose maybe you can send
me your your presentation i i i
will uh yeah but i have videos so uh for me
i don't understand stop sharing
and i'm really sorry because i have to update
my zoom and the new one is not working um
uh application windows okay maybe i can try
that one and here do you see my side my screen
hello no no no it's black it's black yes yeah only
black black it's black black but it's written you
start to share your screen yeah i think i have
a problem with my display system i don't know
um i don't know what is happening
ugh
do you don't see anything you don't
see anything telling that you are
sharing your screen but we don't see anything
arriving on the screen actually okay let's try
i again understand
you could uh hear her monitor what is the
first time so yeah i i this is what i'm doing
do you see something no an ear
so you don't see my monitor at all right now
i'm sorry about that
i don't see
i don't understand this usually
should work except for this problem of
maybe you can reconnect your
your last your second screen and
this is what i have done okay but you don't
have to jump here you don't see anything
what if you sorry hello everybody what if you send
your uh slides via file sender send file sender
to download and yeah but the problem is that i
have movies uh you have too many yeah okay sorry
okay but i will maybe i can i don't
know why why you don't see the screen
you can change the order of a presentation for
example you can search mangalysan and marekson
then we have uh some yeah
yeah but uh this reason this will not
solve the just sharing problem i will have
let me try something you don't see anything at all
right now or a black screen or something like that
just a black screen
okay so i'm sorry i i don't know what uh what
i can do there okay i can sign for sure i can't
send the presentation but uh this could be
a pity because there are a lot of movies
uh going on um maybe i will okay you can
switch i will try to reconnect and uh
maybe just try to disconnect and reconnect maybe
i can't try that
yeah but
new show let's try new share
let's try something else you
still don't see anything no right
and i'm really sorry about
that i don't know what to do um
this usually works except for this actually
appears this morning so maybe yes we can
close a general program jim application
then early connect to a gene
okay i will do that i will
disconnect and reconnect again
so maybe i don't know if someone has a question
maybe we can take one question yes it's uh
it's better to use this tank to hold qa so if
anyone has a question to audience from audience
or culture if you have questions also to professor
tokui and professor asaya you can ask them also
yes uh i have a question for mr tokuy
how did you create a gun for a release because
i think it's very difficult to uh create a
discriminator for what is a light and least and
a long reason on my song could you please share
it's very good
could you please say something
i can see your sharing monitor and sharing
window but i cannot hear your voice
foreign
how can i can we do
yeah i'm looking forward
very strange
oh
okay do you see my screen now
uh yes i can see okay so i will
go fast to so if possibilities so i'm jean-claire
i'm working as a robotician so i'm not an artist
at all i'm working in a team which is called ifa
sauce which is working basically on providing
assisted device for free people um probably that
i don't see my screen so i cannot go up and down
okay so what are the benefits for
scientists to work with athletes
this is the question i have to raise what are
the benefits for artists to work with scientists
those opposite and our other application
domains may benefit from such a collaboration
it's difficult to work with artists for a
scientist and i assume that it's difficult
for artists to work with scientists because
there are a lot of problems so what are
the benefits for scientists to work with
artists well in our research institution
it's not really expected and sometimes
it's even seen as quite suspect furthermore
from an evaluation from a scientist evaluation
viewpoint it's difficult to evaluate because we
don't have indicators and collaboration with
artists requires a huge understanding effort
what are the benefits for artists to work with
scientists well it's a major difficulty is
that the scientist is some kind of in between
between the artists and the work because them are
many of the artists are not aware of technological
possibilities so they have an attitude of
self-censorship that limits the creativity and
they're also the understanding effort for our
people uh they have also to understand
scientists uh do you still hear me i'm
not sure because i have absolutely
no sound no yeah it's okay so
let's let's go to to a practical example to show
you that in spite of these drawbacks we have
the possibility and it's very interesting
possibility to collaborate with artists
i will illustrate site on this example where we
have a robot which is called the cable driven
parallel robot and the purpose of this robot is
to be able to move the point b that you see on the
drawing the platform with this guy underside moves
his platform in all direction x y z so we can
raise the platform go to left go
backwards and upward and to do that
we have four cables which
are attached to the platform
and are also attached on the winch at point a
and the winch allowed to change the cable lengths
and by an appropriate control of the cable length
we can change the position of the platform at will
oops
uh there is an application of this kind of robot
in the earth's domain which is assistance to
mobility for freight people for example really
making transfer operation helping them to go
for example to go to a sitting from a sitting
position to a standing position and also for
working assistance with the benefits of providing
autonomy they are able to do something that
before they were not able to do alone which
improves self-esteem improved social relationship
and it's also very interesting for doctors
for monitoring the health of the subject
because this platform is instrumented to give
medical information so let's just show me a a
short video if it works i hope you can see
the video uh you see your passion on the bed
the robot is coming down the patient is in
a medical harness and i'm losing the job
but basically the passion can do it alone
the robot will lift the passion to move her
in a wheelchair so she will be now again
fully autonomous i will stop the video
but already this robot has this kind of having
incursion of art so for example maybe you
know the pink singer and this is one of her
public performance she moves over the crowd
using this robot and you can see
she will do something very french
on the screen you don't see the video no video
not this one not the previous one as
well pdf sorry but okay this is probably
the same issue with my queen i
will skip that for the sake of time
in 2018 we have a magic encounter with
an artist whose name is ann valerie gas
during a workshop devoted to the use of robot in
architecture and valerie was looking for a machine
with the purpose of 3d printing a
structure on large scale dozens of metals
the printing material is glass microbeads
the machine has to follow a fixed trajectory
and deposit layers of glass powder but there is
no gluing element in the boiler so that the
structure slowly collapse after each layer
and an exhibition of this structure
was scheduled for the summer of 2019
in an art center located close to paris
we get interested in this project
because we have made a huge
effort on the theoretical modeling and control of
this kind of robot we are interested in long-term
deployment because this allowed to test the
robustness of our system and especially to
detect failure understanding why something
has failed and detecting unexpected behaviors
the objectives we have was basically increasing
the safety and performance of the system
for dealing with uh our assistance problem
so you see a picture of the exhibition place
it was huge uh the length was about 40
meter so it's about 20 meter 25 meter
you see there's a drum that is moved by the robot
i will not show the video it's it's
basically bad but i cannot do anything
to get that also maybe i try maybe let me
try something uh i hope i will not lose
maybe you switch the video now
i can see the video okay
and now it's deploying the powder on the structure
okay we'll stop the video move back to the
talk i hope you see the the slide now um
so some result of this exhibition the exhibition
lasts for one month and a half the robot traveled
for more than four kilometers walking in
average four hours and fifteen minutes per day
uh 76 layers of glass powder were deposited
which represents 1.5 tons of glass
and we have some failures one cable
breakdown during the installation
and two small failure encoder on one axis
model but so was it was not really important
uh next we move to icra 2020 the same uh
exhibition was scheduled to be part of
uh the exhibition part of a big
robotics conference which is
whose name is aikra which uh have 5000
plus atlantis in paris during june 2020
we have improved the system but unfortunately
iqra was postponed because of the coffee
and our new exhibition will take place during the
summer of this year in a museum close to to this
lesson learned from art to science we have
received a huge benefit in taking part of the
exhibition from a scientific viewpoint we are a
single team in a world which is able to master a
very difficult issue in this kind of robots
furthermore this experiment those are very
unique test bed for researchers
working on new information
dunes formation modeling but still many of the
colleagues our research school indicates that
more or less valley yeah could
you please back to the pdf
too we see the stop the video so
could you please back to pdf okay um
let me see
okay now you sh okay you schematic
so i'm backing up lesson learned um
from a scientific viewpoint this
experiment was very interesting
but still many of our research colleagues states
more or less overly that this is not real science
it's also said that the government's
level that interdisciplinarity is
very good is a necessity but in the practice
of such official speech is quite different
because the evaluation committee are not
very comfortable with such a collaboration
uh what we need also is that discussion with
doctors and artists have a lot of similarity they
have a different language they have a different
level of scientific knowledge but for us it's
quite uh interesting because this exhibition
has facilitated our communication with doctors
now lesson learned from science to
art many artists believes that that
animating an artwork is a complex and
expensive task this is no more true
even for motion except for very large artwork
uh to illustrate that in 2015 we have uh organized
a workshop called computer science for art which
results so it was a five day workshop which
resulted in a concept at the end of the workshop
with the device developed by the artist during
the workshop and i can show you a picture of
this concept you see some strange machines that
were making music both on the ground on the table
you see a dancer uh for example the dancer as an
accelerometer on so that the music was changing
according to a motion so i moved to conclusion
and sorry for the delay uh for a scientist
wondering on domains quite different from our
main research field is very fruitful this allows
us to develop new algorithms new software newer
methodologies and all this work may be used for
other research topics in our case working with
artists has allowed us to improve our medical
device facilitate our discussion with doctors
but also to better understand human accepta
acceptation of the device which is quite essential
for us and to better understand the pasture needs
so this will end up my presentation and sorry for
the technical problem thank you for your attention
thank you very much for uh
i understand this uh conclusion very much uh so
this time uh this is the end of a session one and
uh from now uh we'd like to have some accurate
session so if any and anyone has a question
for the speakers could you please raise your
hand or say something from my microphone
hello
chris as i said
no
maybe you started a question
uh quick you know maybe you can
yes i have so many questions uh sensei uh
i'm very impressed by your presentation
is very good to improve advance the possibility of
music so i'm very impressed by your work how can i
say the guitar with a vibration so how what is the
initial motivation of to create this kind of data
okay so uh as i said one of the
fundamentals of the rich project is to
state that creativity shared with the machine
can only be an emergent process that will
that will appear in in the course of interaction
and uh so so that you cannot really uh
describe what is creativity for a machine
and maybe this this doesn't have even
meaning but you can describe creative or
co-creative processes that are emerging
because you have a complex interaction
between agents artificial or humans who are
related by a cross-learning
phenomenon so once we have uh
moved into this realm we have realized that in
order to really have this convergence between
cyber augmentation which is augmenting the
the the capacities of agaris of algorithms
and human augmentation which is augmenting
the capacities of human towards the algorithm
we needed we really needed a physical step that
is a step where there would be some embodiment of
the human into the process of interacting with
the machine so the guitar is only the first uh
try that we make the first step of of trying to
to to create the condition for such a physical
embodiment of the human by embedding the algorithm
into a physical device that the human really has
against his body and feels like an extension
of the of his body but it is just the first
experiment of course we would like to design many
other instruments or any kind of devices where
this emergence of co-creativity between human and
machines will be really the result not only of an
intellectual process but of a physical embodiment
of the human and maybe and maybe sometimes because
we we had a robotics presentation just before and
maybe also a physical embodiment of artificial
creators too thank you very much i'm very
impressed by your idea co-creativity with machine
and then i one question to mr tokui and i already
asked the question so could you please answer it
so how can that how i train my gun model
on listen that was question correct okay
so maybe i was not so clear about my project
so the first step was uh to train a normal gun
model a generative otherwise a network model on
this data so it's i think relatively easy for
you know gans network to capture the the essence
of within pattern but i think i thought it's just
another imitation of human creativity in a way
that's why as a second step uh i added another
discriminator to the original gun framework
then the second discriminator is not is not
expected to classify uh training data from uh uh
at least artificial data but it's expected
to classify the genre of music generated
so
the original uh discriminator
was uh trained to classify
the real data from the situation right that's the
uh the core concept when it was about a network
then i added a second discriminator which
does the classification of musical genres
so the origin uh that's right the the generator
was uh uh trained to confuse not only the original
uh discriminator but also the second gen
classification discriminator so i expect
at the end generator will be able to generate
something that sounds like a realism pattern but
uh this is patterns that
don't belong to any genres
the original idea was when you think about artists
maybe uh so think about uh any famous ladies
picasso for example so he started to uh you
know uh trying himself to uh capture the the um
let me rephrase again uh so picasso
or any other artist should start
painting uh to imitate somebody
else's style right so i want to be
like this artist or that artist but uh because
or any other artist at some point they start uh
try to deviate from the existing
styles so there is some kind of uh
like uh i can say uh the conflict between
like staying in the existing style
and also like deviating from the existing
style so there is very delicate balance between
these two directions so i wanted to make
realize that conflict within the gown framework
yeah i understand okay uh you mean that uh
all artists have uh their own discriminator
in their own the one is to imitate another
dish and another discriminator is to
escape from the uh traditional uh at art so i
understand that it's very interesting and it works
can you hear me i have a question
for your presentation and
i understand that you are a scientist and
uh have collaborated with us artists so
is there any a point that the important point
uh to corrupt suspect successful collaboration
with artists artists what is the point
yeah
this is we have to adopt a very different
different uh mind when working with artists
compared to other work we may do with companies
and stuff like that for two reasons uh because
they have the main for many reasons in fact
they have a different language and we have
a different language so we have to understand
each other sometimes we use the same word but
with different meaning so that we need to create
some kind of dictionary between the two community
then the artists are not always aware of all
of our technological and scientific constraints
well what is really uh make me
afraid some in some time is that
when artists tell me oh i have just a minor
detail to change the system the last time they
the artists tell us because we work with many
different artists but the one we are working
with right now the last time she tell me that
results in 400 hours of work changing everything
uh but it's okay uh at the same time we really
learn from the way people are seeing our work
the view of the artist is very different from
the view we have and it's very close to what the
passion tells so it's very important to have this
discussion with us because it's opened our mind
thank you very much wonderful episode and thank
you for all and then we'd like to have some uh
uh
can you read the chat screen magazine
has a question who to uh to question
sharing the same point of view uh which are the
ownership i see and this is not question hashing
then i'd like to have a coffee break to uh for
now and we can see the uh screen of a video
from arya material and you can see the
video from i took in this state in europe
with a cup of coffee
is
foreign
the machine
okay
foreign
is
five years ago i saw some small demonstrations
of it doing like really expressive remapping
from like gesture drawing to something somewhat
photographic i thought that that was an amazing
way to encapsulate knowledge of the figure is
in a neural network i can see a lot of the same
challenges that the neural network will try to
understand that an artist tries to understand
the artist controls it from his imagination and
his ideas and then he kind of confers the routine
that's what i discovered that i was able to do
with the ai at a university i did arts
but engineering was my primary degree
my work is somewhat of the understanding from
engineering and then my artistic study as well
and so a lot of my photography
initially was to support
my my own understanding but
also the anatomy lectures
and that's usually how the the project starts
with kind of a concept that i visualize in
my imagination and then i try to see if
it fits within the techniques that i've
explored whether it was possible i guess one
of the reasons why maybe my stuff is different
i try really ridiculous ideas just to see how
interestingly they fail that part of the process
is maybe a scientist or a researcher but even as
an artist the failure is sometimes beautiful i
understand the boundaries of what machine learning
can do and then just test it and see what happens
hello
from japan uh his name is akira
just approached the idea of creating characters
because he worked for me was like really
mind-blowing i decided to uh to find my my way
as well i'm trying to convince myself to finish
so what i want to do is like a massive
project i would say like 10 000 different
creatures the tools allow
me to work on at this scale
and i want to try to see what comes out of it
oh
yes
hello
something
foreign
okay uh thank you very much
so i'd like to restart the session
from now we'd like to start session two
after first the first presentator is professor
lionel obadiar from university of lyon 2.
what do you say thank you very
much for attending this simple gym
could you please start your presentation
i'm trying you hear me yes i can hear you
all right fine i don't have videos and i hope
everything will feel right for my presentation
oh and i'm really happy and to be there thanks
for the invitation i see that there are a couple
of people that i know around the table but it is
another story so i share my presentation right now
and
i can see can you see it yes all right let's
go for it um i'm just trying to have this um
uh well well well i'm sharing but i want to have
this okay i'm going like that okay do you see
just one one slide okay perfect okay great uh
this is a very long title um and a very short
reflection that you will see and uh i'm a social
and cultural anthropology specialized in religion
asian religion to be a clear and i've recently
since years a couple of years i'm converting
myself to the state anthropological study of
digital technologies aaa robotics and and so on
so um just one point if i have a problem for
the presentation since i do not see all right
i do not see my screen name yeah um so a couple of
reflections starting from fieldwork that i've been
conducting season since one two years ago i tried
to submit an erc advance but uh unfortunately and
they contrary to other colleagues around the table
it was not successful this time that it will be
resubmitted this year but digital magic and i'm
quite glad to hear that uh professor merely talk
about magic but in in the context of robotics
this is exactly what i'm trying to explore now
um so i will talk about today uh um humans
and the the tendency and the and the trends
in in robotics uh and in war society to consider
that robots and all these kind of 3d aaa forms uh
have to be human shaped and what kind of cultural
imagination it brings at the forefront of the
agenda of a reflection of technology and culture
technology and society and technology and history
so we all know that the digital revolution impacts
uh coming in there a wide range of form and effect
in now uh we all agree that we live in
networked connected world and society
and interaction with these devices small ones
big ones have become natural and natural means
in our lexicon culturally accepted so we are many
now studying these new attitudes representation
and cultural frameworks and imagination that
give means to technology as they infused society
and daily lives and there is this kind
of interaction in between technologies
and culture and society complete and and
ongoing uh feedback in between the twos
my anthropological point of view um it's
culturally focused it's comparative and
i'm conducting ethnography of labs exhibitions
enterprises university everywhere where i can
find people that are trying to design develop
test use and socially distribute these very
strange devices called aaa and robots so i'm in
the second month i'm professor an entrepreneur at
the university of lyon but i'm in the second
month right now in two labs the first one is
center for the study of internet and society so
this is all about um communication device and
the sharing information and so on and i'm
also associated a member of the institute
the systematic religion of the robotic institute
for intelligent system and robotics where i'm
conducting my field work and among other places
where i'm doing this field works and my paper will
emphasize images and belief through attitudes
children expression and cultural expression
thing at large including artistic one but i will
not talk about hearts in this presentation today
this course on robots especially robots rather
than a and other digital device this focus is
mainly due to the fact that robots and indeed
raise the crucial issue of human shape form of
uh technological creations so this paper is not on
art except that i'm participating on a uh ongoing
research with people that who are working on
heart this is a seminar untitled robots on stage
interdisciplinary conversions between robotic and
theater this is a network and people are working
together you can see an image of what they do they
are studying plays and robots in place and aaa in
plays and and this is one of the place that i've
been studying and presented in this network but
my focus will be on arts let's say popular arts
the movies literature and online these robots a.m
and other so-called creators as seen from the
side of social sciences and humanities means
not users but designers to users on the human side
and the empirical studies demonstrate that um we
have the evidence that a is everywhere but still
it is nowhere because sometimes with the lack of
materiality and the previous uh papers underscore
this point that we have to materialize and the um
it was on your own paper uh put emphasis on
the materialization and visualization of these
of these devices and software so it depends on
the perception of their silence and materiality
and the same for the degree of reality of the
integration of this device in our life unless
i left beside the issue of cultural difference
in between foundations japan and france and the
united states and so on and um countries with a
lower economic development for instance where the
issue of this technology is an issue of cultural
framework by which this technology are understood
is raised in a quite different way but we'll talk
about culture and society in general excuse for
the very very fast generalization then this is
important to take into account that there are the
inequal social and cultural distribution of device
and their availabilities skills and knowledge and
i heard uh several times this morning the issue
of failures the issue of not understanding the
issue of something that's something wrong in the
in the behavior of the machines and still this is
really important to understand oh as well what
humans provide as meanings and especially when
it's about non-rational means um again these
robots aa software and algorithm and so on
uh uh distributed on a different scale they are
very small one that i that is hidden for instance
in in a in a smartphone application and other ones
that take the shape of a big robot that you can
face you can have a face-to-face interaction
then one thing is striking is the fact that um
not most not all but a significant
part of these devices are shaped
against the uh human face or human shaped or
human body shape um and it raised the question
uh how are we trying to make new humans or
are they still machines and it raised the
outcomes of the issue of mimesis in between
humans and machine on both sides for instance
besides um the issue that social sciences
and humanities are trying to raise and
trying to explore is the interaction in
between these humans and devices and the
correspondence in between human to human social
relationship and human device relationships and
in reality only in imagination and this is
a war scenario for science fiction movies uh
machines to machine communication against human
that you know that this is a really this topic
and a quite widespread scenario of
robots against humans this is one of the
most used uh let's say a background by which we we
imagine uh the the future in movies especially in
in in famous north americans so
we have different side different
forms of materiality from flat devices
screen that are everywhere on 3d devices
robots for instance and 3d that can be real if you
see a machine acting that's why fights on the uh
professor merely as demonstrated but also
uh you can see also 3d uh device this is a
3d representation but what's new uh as an
anthropologist i'm interested in the fact
that they are continuities and rupture in the
relationships in between humans and material
environment through techniques and um i'm
quite fond of this theory that imagine that
there is kind of a ongoing relationship to
uh materiality and to things that we shape
so humans seems to have always been
interested in mediating their relationship to
reality thanks to technology at large start
with very very primitive technologies and it
end up in hyper modern and quick massive wave of
all these devices that are colonizing our life
robots conversational agent algorithm software
robots connected objects and so on for many
different purposes domestic military education
artistic purpose for instance aid generated
by arts or a as inspiration for artists as a
representation then we live in this new ecosystem
of so-called anthropology significant other are
mediated so the anthropological outlook on this
is that if we raise issues regarding our
relationship to a technological device and
robots for instance there are already topics like
ethics and trust this has been already treated and
discussed by psychology philosophy and law but ssh
can bring like a lot of dimension taste and proof
uh from the appeal to robots and and aaa and the
belief in these devices are animating by something
and then anthropology sorry for uh insisting
on this point but uh want to highlight
how humans are in practice creative with machine
and how also they inject imagination futuristic
scenario and even present scenario and how the
scenario infused society and my interest raised in
the fact that this scenario also impacts different
sectors society including technological ones
means that the people that are building these
technologies are actors like uh all all other
actors and they are um influence uh from the best
for the worst influenced by this imaginary frames
and then i will focus on image and imagination
through these screens and visual culture
but let's start for the beginning and
these new mechanics automats robots
located according to the frame of imagination
at the frontiers between humanity and the
rationality between fiction and realism and
especially human human with robots that capture
maybe most maybe more than even all the other ones
um this kind of imagination and then there is an
interesting discussion in robotics right now uh
the um tracing back to meteorological routes this
is a widespread tendency and there are two trends
that if you as an anthropologist read literature
in robotics not not very technical but more open
to history and culture and you see that there are
um sub-community of roboticians that think that
uh ar robots are in rupture with ancient ancient
forms means that it used to be some kind of
representation and either human shape the
things uh quasi human for instance talos that
you see that has been built by ephrais and the
feistos have already been mentioned uh today not
not the program but the the ancient uh greek code
and uh other ones that think that air and robots
are only the continuity of an ongoing mythological
mental scheme in the human brain and these
continuity can be seen as well in what is called
now the animistic design of new technologies
and the idea that there is something inside
something that is hunting the technology something
like a soul or something that does it above or
beyond um the rationality and the purely mechanic
uh life of things and this even turns to a
modern religious robot i take two examples here
and one in china and one in the west these are
robot priest and in some context even the
religious system clearly accept the presence
of robots but as vehicles of belief and one
thing is really important is that we are
witnessing something really really different now
it's a belief in robots and they believe in a as
religious schemes as as a religious object
and to mention the rise of the thanks to uh
because of lewandowski i used to be a an
engineer at google the first church of
aaa that considered that air is a godlike create
but these robots and i focus here only on robots
it comes under a vast array of types and
prototypes you can have small parts of
the body and you can have the full human humanoid
body and this is thanks to uh uh also a clear and
quick advance in uh personal robotics in biomimi's
sensor elaboration algorithm-inspired emotions and
and so on that makes some of the uh organizations
and enterprises creating robots uh attempting to
create robots more and more resembling to
human bodies and if you allow me a slogan
because anthropologists like to produce slogan
we shifting from bios the system setup to buy us
life within these robots and uh this is a
kind of witnessing or revealing unveiling
this obsession for anthropomorphism and and
one thing is surprising striking is even the uh
representation of aa as a software the flat device
is entropromorphized as you can see on the on the
on the small picture on the right uh because
of intelligence and intelligence it's supposed
to be in the brain uh but there are also other
other theories about intelligence uh anyway um
all this brings us to the idea that we start from
and end up in the representation of human body
and then these new programs in human centered
a.a and robotics tend to respond or seem to
respond to this human tendency to consider
technology as a replication of living real
real hard actions but these humans are flat
or 3d almost human or meta human and so on um
range among very different uh
forms and only the adjective
seems to validate and you keep the human
substantive noon and you take a lot of
they inspire a lot of adjectives depending
on what you mean and there are at least three
epistemological regimes that you can raise
after this adjective for instance they said
like humans almost humans are meta-humans
if you consider that these humans resemble
humans only if they are almost human that they
tend to be human that they will be one day
as human or just like human and the meta humans
is they are supposed to be above humans and in my
research i'm conducting a interesting experience
in which i i ask people to react in faith in
front of all these meta humans for instance you
see that on my screen this is on the left but
on your screen it may be on the right this is
this they are quite handsome lady this but this
person does not exist because it's a a generated
face and also there are um these double humans
for instance this character of star wars that
was his towers one and died in the meantime
and was recreated through aa techniques
to incarnate a new character in recent uh
star wars movie even if he's dead but he has the
same face he has the same movement and of course
he has the same voice and the uh digital human
experience it's also interesting because it's a
conversation conversational agent with uh um face
attitudes so you feel like you are talking with
something that is almost human not really human
it's in between and creating a very very strange
um different ways to uh being human race of
course a series of questions and i'm trying to
frame them after um different questions
and different theoretical patterns to uh to
put concept on them uh first the issue that
has been raised previously or as well the
acceptance of these virtual humans uh we
i'm talking in front of people from japan
so mori's famous uncanny valley is still a
concept that will still discuss but was just
a very specific step in the perception and
interaction with a very specific type of of
machine and robot but the uncanny valley has been
widespread in the meantime and now this is a huge
concept that we can uh manipulate and redefine in
order to understand what what's the thrill that
you have when you meet these non-humans but
they are also human they are in between and
this is uh the open door to uh understanding the
very magical uh thinking uh that is in between
humans and mesh so these devices assume different
forms they are co-operative functional therapeutic
friendly assistive and so on and they create a
vast array of emotion as well but these emotions
are mixed together they create anxiety fear for
instance people are really afraid of robots thanks
are due to science fiction movies or literature
but also because they are across the road of of
of robots and uh but this is not always the case
most of the of the time the people have fun with
robots and there and to a certain extent
and a very specific context they also feel
empathy and love and sense of security but uh i'm
talking about this therapeutic robot's name paul
which is made for all people with a psychiatric
psychological trouble and then um they are
something that is coming in between what i call
the three t but uh this isn't that time and if it
doesn't work uh please tell me and please create a
space for discussion in order to contradict these
these um these atoms to uh theorize uh the human
to robots relationships the tools of this robot
are first tools but they are also toys we are
playing with these devices and coming back to
this in in a second and they are also conditions
i mean temptation because we create something more
than a relationship we get also emotions and
we are committed to this device for instance
uh this kind of uh obsession with this device
up to uh sexual desires because now we are
witnessing the rise of sexual robots and not only
in asian countries but also in europe and north
america and then i think that and this may be also
a certain way to get closer to the artistic milieu
thinking about play play in three different
terms of three different definitions of the terms
first is playing with reality we are in a game
and there is something happening that we know
this is not exactly reality but we are trying
to play with reality and the second is to play
in a non-real but real context i mean playing
like you are a character in a theater then you
knew you know that you are doing something that
seems real but it's not real that's like a game
but now you are playing like a character and all
this brings us to play as fun because um people
enjoy uh doing this thing they enjoy they are they
have a lot of positive emotion and they are also
counterbalanced by negative emotions at that time
but these emotions this effervescence uh against
uh robots and the relationship with robots give
rise to really interesting scenarios from the
science fiction and there are four examples of
robots that are purely autonomous imaginative
they are driven by emotions even if they are
not supposed to have emotion for instance in the
the lady on the right is a robot named arisa in a
series that you can find on netflix better than us
and she ends up in sacrificing herself to
prevent the life of the family and she is
in love with the dad of the family but there as
you can see also yule bruner just before um is
uh is a pure uh emotionless robot he's killing
people in the first movie in the 70s of um of
west westworld but he's driven by anger so um he
shows no emotion but he's killing people because
uh he wants to he wants revenge against the human
all this is developed in the realm of scenario in
the real imagination and so on but on the field
when i'm studying uh for instance in the easier
this uh this robot that you can see on the on the
left the so-called baxter robot in which their
motion um trying to trying to make this motion
more sophisticated and the uh two examples taken
from an exhibition in which they are collaborative
robots small ones that are supposed to be vacuum
cleaner robots collaborative with each other and
the famous paper which is welcoming people at the
uh start the uh at the door of the exhibition
and then we get back to a crude reality and
one of the researchers in robotics told me we
are quite far from terminator and around three
and then why there are so different narrative
and um you know that we know we all know that
technologies are embedded in nets of meaning and
to enter it in this narrative but uh do these
autonomous devices need narrative and of what kind
and i allow myself the the chance to divide this
narrative in between scientific narrative and
fiction narrative even if they mix each other
the distinction between the the two of them is
just purely theoretical but scientific narratives
tell history of technology and fiction narrative
that history about about technology and leave room
to very strange things that are coming up to be
reality right now for instance imagining that
there are robots everywhere like in the drawings
helping children helping elder people and bringing
parcels to homes and so on and making love with
a robot find something that you can imagine but
these two images are also counterbalanced
by the fact that we uh uh already have uh
uh virtual girlfriends in japan and uh so
this wasn't essay um and and the papers in
helping for elder people in their homes so
we are not quite far from scientific and
fiction narrative in the reality that we are
living but the most interesting is not that
okay we can explore and explore and explore these
fictional narratives but these narratives end up
being storytelling for robotics organizations
and enterprises first there are a lot of people
are telling us that this is the story this
is a theological narrative we are going
towards the inescapable origin of robots in
society and that's almost human in society and
there are two famous enterprises that use a lot of
uh media technologies such as youtube to produce
uh different videos uh hanson robotics and boston
dynamics they are very famous and the first one is
created sofia this human shape robot face which
is able to have a conversation with the humans
and these are very famous very uh sports uh robots
that are keen to accomplish very very uh difficult
motions and these are very spectacular performance
and they are broadcast intentionally by these
enterprises and this is fascinating for the wide
audience and a lot of people discussing this as
oh this is the future robots you see that women
robots and these uh these very strong and even um
military robots and but this is upsetting
for the robotician i'm working with
they said okay this is just spectacular
things but this is not the reality of robotics
as it is developing right now but
interestingly uh these same atoms to
broadcast the um the performance of robotics
brings about dystopian scenario and this is all um
except for the uh killer robot uh down in the
slide but the two ones the robots is fighting back
boston dynamics roadways is fighting back against
human and uh sofia van hansen robotics telling
okay i will destroy humans these are fake um fake
videos but um this means that the kind of uh janus
side of the of the coin when you try to broadcast
an eutopian future and said okay we live with
this very very powerful performance and very
powerful robots and immediately they are also
contrary visions and contrary imaginations and
then it brings me i'm almost finished to the what
i call the cultural walls in digital revolution
because my approach is also a sociological one
i'm trying to understand position discourse and
framework of imagination and the way they are
intentions and from this field work i'm framed for
ideative attitudes to aaa and robots especially
robots in this case what i call technologies
that means engineers and technicians that are
elaborating robots and most of them told me that
okay this is all but spectacular screen and this
is a software and we are trying to frame algorithm
and then to see to test the movement and the part
of the law and so on and this is quite long and
quite rigorous uh way of of doing things and on
the other side they are what i call technologies
don't leave guys that come on tv and write books
and say okay the future of the digital age will
be robots everywhere sometimes they are the same
elon musk for instance is a pure technology
and uh these prophets of the digital age
and describe the future as a full of these devices
may be it for uh critic critics be it for kind of
valorization of this also there are technophilians
developers and users that are fascinated by these
new technologies and technophobians okay four
positions but the surprise come by the fact that
we are not only and not really in a face-to-face
confrontation with you on the one side those
who believe in the future of robots and robotics
and say okay there are technologies we live robots
will be like gods like new angels like new spirits
of the time and the other side technologies that
bring this back to the crude reality and
saying that this is not exactly that this
we have to be rationalists this is all all but all
that reality and more most of the time we find in
the scientific literature this kind of tension
between rationality and irrationality but it's
much more complex than that because first i
give two examples technologies for instance can
be technophobians and in my field work i met some
people that create robots but fear the development
of aaa in the same time these are the same people
and this is the complexity of human feelings and
human attitudes and for instance on the other
way uh technophilians people that like this
technology are not always always technologies and
most of the user in your ignore the process on and
the design of creating technologies and finally
technologies can inspire but not always and annoy
but also inspire technologies for instance we
know that in france they are they have been not in
france not only but elsewhere invitation from the
government um and the organization and invitation
for scientists and authors to imagine matching and
scenario for the for the future so it's not only
coming from the technological mid and slide
and i'm finished and sometimes technologist
meets technology and there is at least one
enterprise in france i'm doing field work with who
level their products enchanted tools and i set up
even a marvel section because when they create aaa
and robots they know that they are designed with
their own history and the imaginary framework they
sell you the robots and the cultural and symbolic
universe of the robot they all come together
and like alice and wonderland in the same
time you cannot have without the others and
this kind of reconciliation in between fiction and
science fiction between imagination and technology
uh then uh this is thanks to imagination robots
then there are more much more in the line of
social exception acceptation and and this
enterprise is supposed to be on the technologist
really rationalist regional side uh leave room
for uh imagination and uh help this creative
relationship uh with robots and a.m and blur the
frontiers and give party ground for imagination
i come from the east side of the of the creators
of rob and at final reflection just a sum up of
these points this is all again an ongoing research
and these are some results but not all the results
um this paper was just to reflect upon the issues
of sciences i determined to a digital revolution
and a very specific object in digital revolution
especially robots and the anthropological point
of view that has been adopted here was from
the bottom from the actor's point of view
and how and why and who produce what kind
of technological imagination or imagination
projected on technologies and these human shape
devices that are present here today are a good
example but are not the only one and all have
been said now i might be counter balanced and
critically converted to other devices and
other conditions of producting and using these
technologies um of course these are technologies
are also source of different kind of images and
surrounded by a different framework of imagination
but my conclusion is creative imagination is not
always where we think it is and the appropriation
of these devices in the media of artistic media
is a key evidence of this point but my look was
on the technological media and the and uh widening
communities of roboticians and this imaginary uh
cultural imaginary then can nurture or prevent
the advance of and in technologies i mean um and
this is my final conclusion we always from side to
side from the beginning of thinking about robots
a and digital technology and producing them and
distributing disseminating them in in societies
and culture think about the the very crucial role
of imagination it means images and ideologies
surrounding these technologies thank you
thank you very much professor obadiah
for wonderful presentation and i
love this kind of topics so i have so many
issues to this i'd like to discuss with you
but uh the first i'd like to start uh the
two three more presentation for this session
then i'd like to discuss all with us so the next
uh i'd like to welcome miss b chen from china
she's artist and she's a great artist
and i'm honored to be welcome here bison
could you please start your presentation
sure thanks eduson for the introduction
um so today i'm going to share some of the
experience i developed after i returned to china
so it's great to to be here and so i'm sharing
the screen now can you see it can you see it
sorry let me just yeah so i will i will ask
my avatar to do this presentation for me today
okay who okay
yes i can hear you no doubt that technology
has played an increasingly important role
since the 20th century humans have
to face multiple crisis and dilemmas
from nature society and humans themselves in such
a closely interconnected world can the collusions
of different cultures and ideas inspire creations
that helps technology develop the better solutions
hello everyone my name is vincent thanks to
dr either for the invitation it's my great
pleasure to be here with other
professionals at this workshop
i'm interested in the relationship between
humans and technology to be more specific
i'm interested in how humans perceive or
understand technology in a different culture
i have studied at m8 design interactions
with professor raby at the london royal
college of arts that's also why a part of my
work includes speculative future scenarios
technology has been around since the dawn of
humanity from stones for hunting to sticks to join
all of which are the products of technology
in human society in this time although
technology is presented similarly in general due
to the globalization nowadays since i moved back
i have found a common phenomenon in china
people have a pretty different view of technology
than what i haven't seen in other countries
there is a park at center of beijing called
temple of heaven which seems to have become
a testing ground for local creativity of
innovation even the toilet in this park have
equipped it with face recognition technology
going to the loo in his park must not be an
overly urgent task like in no times you can
only get the pieces of toilet paper after taking
off your head and your glasses and staring at the
machine for three seconds the slowly dripped
toilet paper is limited each time so if you
need more you may have to repeat the progress
a few times before go into the toilet oh and
you can also get the toilet paper from the front
looking of pikachu i have texted through my phone
there are many more cases here
from a noodles performance robot
to a piano that can grill lamp kebabs to
the shenzhen's smartphones chinese citizens
have unique optimistic altitudes on technology
these attitudes re-establishments how they live
in their living environment which
also influenced my art creations
the ancient chinese cosmology there's a set of
thoughts and rules behind the seemingly magical
talisman it is a virtual miss blended with reality
such as rim making ceremony and at the same time
is the most sensory reflection of how people
at each time have understood their natural
environment resembles the way how algorithms and
data shapes are meant fulu is a thousand talisman
that uses writing a meditation spell and spiritual
power to scare away evil spirits attract fortune
or perceived peace in the space they are hung
up or paced onto fulu is a drawing consisting
of chinese characters with a mythological origin
more than writing that merely describes the word
these characters have a magical relationship with
them that allows them to act upon reality nowadays
the word of network's timo lecra gradually
adopts and even replaces reality benefit tissue's
narrative of data becomes resources or even
capsule the emergence of blockchain technology
and its decentralized worldview make it possible
for internet nomads to build a better life
and these fictions are often regarded
as objective depictions of reality
the character shu in old chinese means method
skill extending from the meaning of the past
shu also expressed both technology and the
witchcraft which presents fiction there are also
cases of fictional transformations of reality
in the records of dynasty in the novel heroes
of wood marine may eventually their depictions of
diced monks and rivers who armed solely with diced
tools and witchcraft were able to overcome the
machines and bring liberation for exploited people
continuing with this fiction or ancient wish of
the qing dynasty i have created a speculative work
a series of contemporary fools for the society
that is entirely overtaken by technology
this attempts to help people break the current
human dilemma that both by the technology
and to explore the value of fictional realities
in this work i invited hong kong
calligrapher quinzo to invent
some food together to harness the invisible
magnetism of algorithms in combination with
ancient beliefs for example the image on
the screen is for bitcoin holders it can
convert any electronic devices into a bitcoin
mining machine for attracting more bitcoins
we decided to let this alternative future
so so now you can get those flu online
technology
new techniques a type of liberation
and autonomy or just enough
use in space be liberated or trapped
in his book
only
thoughts have succeeded in tips but
also helped general products not all asian
essentially in the exact nature like this
hmm
peace on
is is it disconnected
hello b sound are you here hello okay i think
i saw some icons appear on my laptop said
connection is not good can you hear
me now can you hear me now yes yes
okay so i will start sharing again
okay okay can i say it yes okay cool
you
to allow the public to encounter their world
anew a german noise assignment transported 1999
used smartphones on trolley surreal streets of
berlin and google maps recognized this activity
by turning a green street red and automatically
producing a virtual traffic jam on the map
the fictional activity also affected the
physical world where smart navigation
directed cars to alternative routes to avoid
being stuck in this traffic this is not racket
poses potentially to generate fictions often take
as accurate attentions of reality another example
is sunday island image at the right side was
featured by google earth through their satellites
imagery and market in the contemporary digital
charts such as google maps from 1876 until october
2012 when scientists finally discovered that the
island have never existed the marina favor is a
network commissioned by unesco creative cities
to critique the relationship between humans and
technology as game is one of the common mechanism
used in my creative practice i have built a
telephone game with the artificial intelligence
program tits translated in his work the text
is translated between 10 rooted and distant
language families to decipher the original text
after the text has been translated and
re-translated the original meaning is lost and the
cyber formatted linguistic endpoints is obtained
the project results from negotiating questions
such as chameleon be accurately represented in
translation from human accessibility to machine
logic what does it say about us trusting the
perfection of computers over the sentimentally
of humans using these questions as a
foundation running human or philosophical
text through a programmatic data obscures
the language mechanically the resulting text
visual images its final step relieves
on the intuitive and imprecise thinking
that mirrors human perception
english writer and creative
we only see what we look at to look is an act
of choice i think art is particularly important
in this area than ever as everything
in its reality is attached to capsule
by reviving the power of fiction art change the
real world in the current technological context
to generate awareness for technology for
work citizens to rethink their current states
to catalysts for the better futures and
that's my talk today thank you very much
oh wow oh thank you very much uh your
presentation is also an art hard work
very beautiful thank you very
much yeah yeah thank you very much
i have many questions to you but uh i'd
like to proceed to the next presentation
then and let's discuss so i'd like to welcome
mangaly and martin mozarix from inaliya
so could you please start your presentation
yes i'm sharing my screen thank you
and that's
oops so
is it working yes it is indeed um so thank you
again for inviting us and my name is magali and
in the name of indriya cnrs and lucia and
tehrani america we would like to to thank
you dr um koichiro etosan for this invite and also
the french and japanese foundation and early kid
i'm sorry but our presentation is going to be
very different because it's uh to share the
project we are working on at the moment in um help
maritime in the south of france sophia antipolis
and um thank you to all of you for your
excellent and exciting uh presentation and
i'm still very very impressed uh by being
shane as well and it's going to be hard
to talk after her so tehran america is
digital sciences at your fingertips it's
something like we would like people
to discover explore and experiment
so why terrain america because like
gravity digital is like everywhere and yet
digital till divide
people know how to use their phone their laptop
but they don't know how what's behind it and
uh for terra in america it's very important
uh to um engage people and and and share with
them so they can be uh independent with digitals
and what's going on in this in this a new world
so very often we hear that these are not my
cup of tea and despite the very good quality of
qual of science mediation with high attendance
at science fair open doors conferences
courses digital is not yet considered not as
a part of our culture as art is so therefore
we sorry i'm not very up so therefore tyranny
america um wants to disseminate uh the the
knowledge to the largest possible number of
people and we aim at um being a good vector
for digital sciences in education and then bring
equal opportunities for everybody boys and girls
also why terrain america in our territory it's
a very rich territory in interactions with
arts as you may know the south of
france alpha mari timber and provence
was is still a very attractive place for artists
um so many came and stay and and produce in in the
area it's a very rich territory for art schools
and like victorian studios as recently reopened
so cinema interactions lots of students and in
society police and in nice and too long as well
a lot of research centers and private companies so
very big nice area to to share and to to carry on
so the main goal of tehran america was to
bring together the whole digital sciences
actor which were on our territory and it was
to not build well build something new but also
uh bring together all the people to make their
experience and expertise in scientific meditation
their innovation creativity co-activities stronger
also we very um we're very keen in training
teachers professors and and sharing
devices all devices around digital sciences
so tehran america is a project still
it started we are now very i'm
sorry sorry sorry sorry he lost my
we are now supported by our two funding
members cnrs india and universite cote d'azur
we we have fully members from different areas
like research and higher education laboratories
schools association private companies and local
authorities as well our goal is to finally have
a big space to share and to show digital sciences
but not only all the earn their interactivities
but also we are very keen on going in mainly
in interland um area because lots of secondary
schools high schools multimedia libraries
don't always have access to those opportunities
we we have very open we are very open-minded
and we've got like at the moment 150 people
working all together and including
citizens students scientific administrative
staff artists everybody is is very welcome
so to give you a brief history of the project
the project was born in into december 2018.
we were only four at the moment so in in 2 2019
we had to present and convince people and finally
we got a name and a logo which is tehran
america we got our first funding and first a key
achievement for tehran america in 2020 2020 then
2021 um it was time for our um our um sorry our
research centers to sign an agreement
and to encourage us to to carry on
so 2020 is 2022 is a big step for us because we
are going to have a new pad as we said a very
big space 500 square meters where we are going
to put down everything and it's going to be
able um a place for sharing for researchers
and people citizens to come and enter and
visit visitors and attend any kind of activities
and the final goal for terra numerica in 2025
with the help of the local authorities
is to open a dedicated place
to science meditation sorry meditation
popularization of digital sciences and
we had the confirmation a few months
ago so we are going to have like
5 500 meters just for terra numerica and
just next to it same place in sofianti police
5 500 square meters for heart and science
linked to terrain america and in connections
and after that the adventurers goes on we've
got to carry on and work and produce and invent
and be different and attract more people
so this is the place we we are going to
uh invest very soon um where people are
uh will be able to come and and visit and
it will be like the digital science fair all
your all year round sorry and what we want is
to support innovative thinking inspire create
share with everybody who's happy to come and um
also we've got a little well not a little we would
like to develop art and science in our project
and so just let open the
windows on art and science and
as picasso said everything you can imagine is
real and this is what we are doing with terranim
america but not only so we've got um an agreement
with espace archon de and we are going to work we
are already working with them like jean-pierre as
well uh showed you his project he's going to work
with with them as well and we would like to
cross views between artists and scientists
so that could be a different level like for
instance the first example is robert de lune
and you can as an artist the creation
and what an artist at inoria can create
around the knee triangulations producing
um producing algorithm so that's an example
another example could be that that's a neural
networks from another artist statin area and how
your imagination could interpret
neural networks in a different way
one of our scientists frederick avi who could
not be there and dorian mazurik they both work
with this espar concrete and for instance this
is the work of carl andre which is a famous
sculpture american sculpture and it's the queens
of on the work of heart and it's mixing hearts
mathematics and algorithm as you can see also
we've got heart is everywhere and there is another
project which is a spiral is in shape and it's an
approach a multi-disciplinary approach and in this
case we want to erase awareness of observation
reflection via the spiral as a mathematical
object or sharing with science and technology
but not only like for instance the origami um
origami to us could be um a way to also
introduce deep learning but very vulgarated
but deep learning as you repeat the same gesture
to train and to make your origami become alive
so that could be you know lots of connections to
explain science and the interconnections between
um heart history of art and
and whatever okay so we are um
beginning to be a bigger project with a lot of
ambitions and any contributions would be very very
uh welcome um we we can share with you
seminars creative and innovating project
and also from what we heard this morning new
certificate new scientific research approaches
and it would be very uh important for us
to carry on any kind of collaboration so
this is just a little video i hope it works and
huh
oops
so thank you very much to harry gatou
gozaimasu we will we heard about your
summer school at the beginning and we would
be very happy to maybe uh collaborate with you
also in next november in society police at
indriya we're on organizing an aca tech with
young students and researchers and one
of the major group research area would
be heart and sciences because we believe
we can create and do lots of new things
and we we've got to in in the area we also
hold the project troisi ah koichiro etosan
you you've already heard about it so
you could have a lot of interactions
around ia with a lot of scientists but
not only twice a year tehran america have
called for projects so we've got little finance to
give the opportunity to artists or to scientists
to collaborate and to work together and being a
non-artist and a non-scientific and living with
living and working with scientific and artists
i believe that there is no um that's it's not a
different word it's the same word sometimes
as jean-pierre and some of you already said
the communication the the wording is not the same
but the creativity and your sensitivity is just
the same uh always i often hear mathematician
say oh i'm so happy my algorithm is so beautiful
and it's in the same aspect that an artist could
share his whatever production and also my final
sharing is next time um we we would be very
honored uh to make a little video for tehran
america or whatever and and talk with now
uh toki sensei and maybe have his music
in back in the background to be more
innovative thank you again arigato gozaimasu
thank you very much for your presentation
makali-sang then uh our presentation was
finished for session two so we'd like to
start a discussion of uh of this session
then uh thank you thank you for all then i'd
like to start a question to uh from myself
so why do you say can you hear me yeah i do yeah
maybe you you have a limited time to so i'd like
to start question for you no no i i actually
have plenty of time because if uh if it's
a quarter to ten two two up
past 12 in france this is
one hour left i'm in great britain now so i
have a lot of time not a lot but i have time
uh okay thank you uh i i'd like to ask you the
uh many questions but uh at the first one point
uh how do you think the differences between the
west and the east was for thinking about the
dystopia scenario for the future uh i i think that
there is a uh how can i say increased by from the
fiction nobel for example frankenstein uh as
you know a scientific science fiction novelist
uh isaac ashimov named it as a syndrome
of a frankenstein so how do you think the
scenario is different for the west and the east oh
the question of cultural relativity i heard that
um well um we have the same i have i i i'm jumping
aside and i'm coming back to the discussion right
now i'm also working on another uh um mediatic
and the cultural creator named the zombie and you
know there is huge discussion regarding if it's
a production of the western imagination and if it
can also be rooted in the in non-western culture
and civilization given that the relationship
in between the body culture the imagination of
after after death and so on are quite different
from uh way on the way to another depending
not only on culture but and i'm getting back
to the point on history uh you know that the
the um on not only culture but also history
for instance the the degree of uh historical
trauma that you have for instance for walls
and uh the very specific relationship that you
can have with technology and uh for instance you
japan invented godzilla and now this is the
universal feature now the character that we
we can see everywhere but you invited it and and
this now belongs to the global popular culture
and it can be recognized everywhere and so i think
that there are framework for dystopian scenarios
similar on some aspects with a local variations
regarding the uh very specific national history
uh let's say on the background of global
history but but national histories for instance
and that's why uh there is a huge distribution
of of this uh dystopian scenarios but um if you
allow me just one more second i'm i'm a bit
talkative but just one second this dystopian
scenarios has also grounds for the acceptation
of this for instance the fact that we all know
who is frankenstein creator and we all accepted
that we can create such uh let's say animals or
or human-like creatures regardless of the the
outcomes and the fact that the creator can kill
the the create creator can kill the creator but
you can fear a very specific scheme or object or
sign of symbol but accept it and
dystopian can also be uh imaginary indeed
geological ideological facilitator for the
acceptation of these things in my opinion
interesting i have this kind
of a scientific fiction story
there are so many cultural background differences
so maybe we can deepen this uh kind of stories
very much but uh i'd like to make broader to this
uh topics uh so i'd like to ask you uh uh being
some uh how do you think the uh described stories
from the east side and uh your presentation is uh
wonderful and also it's playful so uh i'm very
interested in your story to a playful future
ah president can you can repeat the question
again sorry uh i think the internet is not
evil in the uh you created the future
scenario as a good site or a prayer site
i'm very interested in where did you come
from this kind of attitude altitude you mean
the work i just created oh yeah okay well i think
it's quite it's quite complicated because as
an artist i think any experience is going to
our creation so i think my creation slightly
starts changing because i was moved back to
china since 2020 and from then i think the whole
involvement and also the people how people are
using the technology and the people's optimistic
altitudes on the technology in this whole
environment is quite shocked me so so that that's
you can see that's my analyze um of how what
happens in these environments like from my slides
just in my presentation and so from that i
was thinking um compared to the study i would
compare to the the life experience um when i was
in london and i seen like quite different view
in china that everyone can so close engage with
the technology that they bring the technology
uh fragments into their daily lives and then so
in that case um i think here everybody is artists
they are creating they're creating um their
how can i say they use their creation to
actually um build the future day by day person by
person and so when i seen this also i was raising
myself as an artist was the responsibility of
being an artist in this technological arrow um
so basically i'm more like critics on
technology through my artworks um and uh
and uh yeah that's that's that's experience again
um from from the from beijing from china here
i'm not sure if i don't say it
yeah it's wonderful answer that
everybody is an artist in china yeah
it's quite like you can't really you can't
really feel which parts is the reality and
which part is fiction it's kind of all
mixed up together the things you see in
it may next day appear in a daily life like in
china you never know every day is a surprise
interesting thank you very much
for sang can you hear me magazine i have a
question for you that how would you like to
make a place to collaborate with
artists in your project can you hear me
nobody saying
he is not in a list of the names anymore wow
okay then
she came here again
if somebody have questions to uh
speakers uh you can feel free to uh
on microphone then start to talk
or please say something from chat
can you hear me
yes sorry shiro i lost you and i had to connect
again ah okay so uh i'd like to i'll repeat the
question to you okay thank you i have a question
uh is it any uh plan to make a collaborative
collaborative space in your project is there
any future plan to collaborate with artists
oh yes indeed we we would like to to do that
i mean jean-pierre is already an example
so far we have approached the ah concrete in
satu but we would like to carry on and extend and
even outside the area the national i
mean the france or elsewhere because like
we are going to have one 1 500 meters dedicated
to art and science and it's very important to
to collaborate and to extend and so there are
so many local artists as well it's a very rich
territory so yes we are very uh keen
on on collaborating uh koichiro with
you or any person who would like and
also it is very important as you said
it's opening a new reflection on science
um aspects like uh with social environment
and with heart and the connections
and i gather our project it's at uh
at um a level just under your creativity
because for us the important is to share
like we explain uh ia with a wooden
machine we've got lots of and it's to make
people more confident and to show them that um
digital a is everywhere but like art is everywhere
as well to us so it's important that people trust
and feel more confident and it's uh it's like
religion has lionel uh i think it was leonel
made them the relation i mean it's everyday you've
got to convince people you've got and especially
after what we've been through with the kovid
you can all see that there is a lack of on on
believing in science or in scientists so the
problematics is everywhere and we've got to um
carry on but yes we will be
very happy to collaborate
i'm looking forward to collaborating with you yes
we ideally we would we would have loved to welcome
you in in march sometimes but because you are
going back to japan maybe next time with pleasure
koichiro yeah thank you very much thank you so
this is a time for discussion so uh is there any
uh questions uh between a speaker to a speaker
uh we we are welcome to talk we have from you
i have one but meditate it will bring us
very far okay i can try to jump here um
since you work with the on the one side there is
a close connection with artists and on the other
side you are working as in in in the heart of
technology um how do you get the issue of crafting
on the one side and creating
on the other side all together
this is not an easy question this is a theoretical
question i'm sorry for that but i know that there
are spaces right now in sciences where creation uh
yeah you know crafting science is really inspired
by by heart and and and reciprocally so uh both of
you are one of you um how do you tackle this issue
well okay we have the main research
area which is assistance for frey people
but at the same time we allowed us to wander
on other topics that are not really connected to
our main research areas it happened in workshop
it happened in meeting well you know quite well
that we have a lot of administrative meetings
and we try to make the best of them meaning
that we have the opportunity to meet other
colleagues working in very different domains
and what surprised me no doesn't surprise me but
what happened is that i see some kind of
convergence in science as well meaning that
for example we have people trying to tackle
numerical fluids problems and it just happens that
if you discuss with them during
lunch you will see that they have
problems that are very similar
to what problem you have and
you have developed algorithm for solving this
problem they have developed their own algorithm
and it happens quite quickly frequently um
that uh well their tools may be quite useful
for us and reciprocally and in fact
it's it's i will say it's just random
meeting uh so we just kiss with lawyers we discuss
with biologists i have a biologist in my team
i will say just the open discussion
there is no systematic way to do it we have done a
systematic approach at the beginning when we move
to industrial robotics to assistance robotics we
spend two years making a lot of interviews with
customers help us medical community
local authorities and really
it was very useful because we learned a lot of
things we learned to avoid a lot of mistakes
which are very easy to make and i think
that with artists it just happens that
it happens once a long time ago the world
spread among the artists there is some team in
south of france which may help us to do whatever
we want so this started accumulating and
the world spreads and that's it but there
is no process for that in my opinion
thank you
sorry sorry so i was saying that uh in my first
life at irkam when i was mostly working on
computer-assisted composition software tools we
we had two kind of interactions between scientists
and artists in in the first situation the artist
would come to the scientist with a problem
for instance a musical problem and would ask for
help and expertise and algorithm and sometimes a
problem that was explained in a very lengthy
way and seemed very complicated actually could
be solved with a very simple scientific or
technological device or a simple algorithm
and sometimes a problem that seemed extremely
simple to the artist and the artist thought that
he would really just need a
little help to to achieve it
would actually become a huge scientific
problem and maybe sometimes an unsolvable one
and this is very very interesting because it
shows that the perception of complexity is very
different between artists and scientists
scientists have issues of computability
which is a very difficult topic as as as you
know and uh things that that are very obvious
in real life uh can become extremely
difficult to model actually in in uh
a quantitative approach and sometimes the artists
have a hard time understanding this because what
is simple for them and or complex and complicated
for them it's totally different from what the
scientists would uh tackle as simple or complex
so so we had this strange relationship in the
first place with the in the situation where the
artist would come to the to the to the scientists
and asked so to speak for a service we had another
kind of interaction which which went the other
way around so the scientists are also creative
and creators except that they create scientific
theories or algorithms or models and they would
come up with ideas of new models new algorithm
new fields and then they would talk about it
because of course we have a lot of places to
talk workshops conferences seminars etc and then
the artist would would come to the scientists and
say oh i never thought about that it's absolutely
fascinating and it gives me an id for a new work
for a new piece maybe we can collaborate and so
in this situation uh uh uh it it it would be it
would be the ideas coming from the scientist who
would inform and influence the artist so that was
a traditional uh divide that was a traditional
dichotomy between uh art and science as
a as a service-based relationship or art and
science as a transfer or influence or transfer
of ids from one field to another it's two very
different approaches and of course we we had
to cope with both but since i've been working on
interactive and creative ai that is designing uh
kind of artificial create creatures that can live
by themselves and interact on stage with musicians
now we're on in a very different situation because
the the the concern now of the musician is how can
how can i have this artificial creature shut up
for a moment because which is which is exactly
a question of control because we don't know
really how to control them for instance we have
algorithm ai algorithm that generate music and do
real-time machine learning in live situations etc
and they play music sometimes in a very smart way
but they they they don't we see we still don't
have the cognitive model of intentionality and
intrinsic motivation and all this that that makes
that that that can help us to decide when to start
and when to stop doing something so generally
generally the the human who starts the computer
and then the computer plays music it doesn't know
when to stop so so the the the human would would
really like to have some more control uh over that
and so we so we are now moving to to uh to a
paradigm of control and how to understand uh uh uh
uh control in the in the case where you have kind
of artificial uh um uh agents uh that that have a
that have a certain autonomy so the problem has
totally shifted to to to this new issue of control
i think just what that
just one thing that uh i have to mention is that
there is a parallel between in our collaboration
with that uh with a collaboration we have with
doctors you have to be quite careful when you
do that for example if you go when you meet a
doctor for the first time and tell him look you
have currently a medical process and i will teach
you how to change it and to do it very efficiently
so you want to change everything then you are
dead you have to learn to be incremental meaning
you have to simply state okay you have a
process i will not change it i will just
help you on a given detail of this process to do
it in a better way or to do it for you something
that you have currently doing we will avoid trying
to do an example when you do a walking analysis
of a patient there is a classical test where you
measure the time the guy takes to make 10 meter in
this straight line so so the surgeon
is looking as at the chronometer
of looking at the way the guy is walking so
the first thing we do is okay we will avoid you
looking at the chronometer because our
machine will measure all the time for you
that's it they say okay because it was no big
change for them and then we say well we can
measure also some of the things for example
we have measured during this experiment this
particularity oh they say oh you can measure
that so incrementally we add things we were able
to do since the very start of the program but we
won't we don't want to say that at the beginning
and the doctors learnt like the artists and when
the request or the suggestion does not come from
us but from the doctors you have measured that but
be possible to measure also that that we know we
have win and it's exactly the same process with
artists in our first collaboration we were just
attacking with a small minor detail in the
artwork showing it can be done and progressively
that you say oh you have been able to do that i
would like to do another thing can you do it for
me and that's okay if you are these steps then you
know that the collaboration will be quite fruitful
you have to be perfect
to fight your to fight your own mind we
say okay we have this problem i know how
to deal with it completely and efficiently you
have to learn that to be careful not do that
yes it is very smart uh approach and
as you say the relation between artists
and scientists is a very delicate one and
one has to treat it uh in a very delicate
yeah way you very much uh for
the cube okay and uh i think uh i we are
almost running out of time for discussion so uh
no
okay uh uh okay uh i'd like to uh uh
conclude this q a discussion session
and uh also uh this workshop so thank
you very much for all participants
in this workshop you know for food
for a discussion in this time so
can i across or who is a speaker for closing
remarks yes i think you can you can conclude here
because i think sebastian the chevalier uh jean
vivian had to left earlier so you can conclude
okay i'd like to conclude this workshop
and there was a wonderful presentation
so many wonderful presentations and
uh there's so many issues to how to
deepen the relationship between uh art
and advanced technology in this society
so i am very thankful to all the participants
and for speakers and audience uh thank you very
much for making this workshop possible uh so i'd
like to to end this workshop thank you very much
thanks a lot thank you thank you very much
thanks everyone thank you thanks
take care bye bye thank you bye